<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?rfc comments="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc inline="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="no"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<?rfc tocindent="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>

<rfc category="std" docName="draft-keyupate-idr-rcn-00"
ipr="pre5378Trust200902">

  <front>

    <title abbrev="Root Cause Notification">
    Root cause notification to solve BGP path hunting</title>

    <author fullname="Keyur Patel" initials="K.P."
            surname="Patel">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 W. Tasman Drive</street>
          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>keyupate@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Chandra Appanna" initials="C.A."
            surname="Appanna">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 W. Tasman Drive</street>
          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>chandra@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Pradosh Mohapatra" initials="P.M."
            surname="Mohapatra">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>170 W. Tasman Drive</street>
          <city>San Jose</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>95134</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>pmohapat@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="John Scudder" initials="J.S."
            surname="Scudder">
      <organization>Juniper Networks</organization>

      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>1194 N. Mathilda Ave</street>

          <!-- Reorder these if your country does things differently -->

          <city>Sunnyvale</city>

          <region>CA</region>

          <code>94089</code>

          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>

        <email>jgs@juniper.net</email>

        <!-- uri and facsimile elements may also be added -->
      </address>
    </author>

  <author fullname="James Uttaro" initials="J.U."
            surname="Uttaro">
      <organization>ATT</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street>200 S. Laurel Avenue</street>
          <city>Middletown</city>
          <region>NJ</region>
          <code>07748</code>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>uttaro@att.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="February" year="2010" />

  <abstract>
   <t>Whenever a prefix is withdrawn using BGP withdrawl mechanism, it
    triggers  a number  of  updates in  certain  scenarios before  the
    prefix is  completly withdrawn from  the entire BGP  network. This
    phenomenon  is  popularly known  as  _path  exploration_ or  _path
    hunting_ and  occurs because  of path vector  property of  BGP. It
    results  in a  series of  unwanted or  redundant  transitions that
    overloads the BGP network.</t>
   <t>This document describes a mechanism  to help limit the amount of
    such  path exploration  by defining  two optional  transitive path
    attributes for BGP: SPEAKERID_PATH and ROOT_CAUSE.</t>
  </abstract>
 </front>

 <middle>

<section anchor="introduction" title="Introduction">
<t>
Whenever a prefix is withdrawn using BGP withdrawl mechanism,
it triggers a number of updates in certain scenarios before
the prefix is completly withdrawn from the entire BGP network. This phenomenon is
popularly known as _path exploration_ or _path hunting_ and occurs because
of path vector property of BGP. It results in a series of unwanted or redundant transitions
that overloads the BGP network (<xref target="I-D.li-bgp-stability"></xref>).
</t>
<t>
It is interesting to note that these redundant transitions can end up triggering
route dampening (<xref target="RFC2439"></xref>, if deployed in the network. Additionally,
route dampening itself is known to cause path exploration in the network due to the delay
it introduces (<xref target="I-D.li-bgp-stability"></xref>). This effectively creates a
spiral effect on BGP instability. Both the generation of unwanted update messages and 
the triggering of route dampening can adversly affect the BGP convergence
time.
</t>
<t>
The problem lies in the way BGP path vector is defined. With a link
state protocol, each router stores a complete view of the entire network and
derives reachability information from that view. In the event of a flap, each
router can correctly determine all paths that suffer from the same root cause.
This is not scalable in large networks in which  BGP operates. By design, 
BGP advertises only the path it is using in terms of ASes to its 
neighbors with each prefix. Unfortunately, this information is coarse even in a simple topology
as the number of possible paths through the routers is quite large. When a route 
is not reachable, because the detail route information is not included, BGP 
selection process may end up choosing an alternative path that is actually not available. 
After sets of such transitions, BGP speaker will resolve this abnormality and 
decide on correct available path based on receiver side loop detection.
</t>
<t>
This document proposes a mechanism to identify unreachable paths 
for which BGP withdrawals are not received and prevent them from being
selected as prefered paths. This helps avoid unnecessary route flapping
within the network. A new optional transitive path attribute, SPEAKERID_PATH
is tagged in BGP announcements as the prefix travels through the network,
essentially creating more granular information about routers in the path.
When a prefix is withdrawn, another optional transitive attribute, ROOT_CAUSE
is attached to the implicit or explicit withdraws that are generated at
different points in the network. This attribute is created once at the
point of occurrence of the fault and gets attached to the resulting
UPDATE message throughout the network unchanged. At a receiving speaker,
the ROOT_CAUSE attribute is matched against
the SPEAKERID_PATH attributes of available paths to help identify and avoid
those that are unreachable since they are affected by the same root cause.
</t>
<t>
Path exploration caused by new prefix advertisements is not discussed in
this document.
</t>
      <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
        "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
        document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
        target="RFC2119">RFC 2119</xref>.</t>
      </section>
    </section> <!-- for Introductions section -->

<section title="Reference Diagram">
<t>
      <figure align="center">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[

                                            
                                      +-------+
                                      |  AS5  |
                    .................R11     R13.......
                   .                  |       |         .
                  .                   +--R12--+          .
                 .                     .                  .
                .                     .                    .
               .                     .                      .  
              .                     .                        .     
          +--R4---+             +---R7--+                 +--R10--+
          |       |             |       |                 |       |   
          R2      R3........... R5      R6............... R8      R9
        . |  AS2  |             |  AS3  |                 |  AS4  |
       .  +-------+             +-------+                 +-------+
       .
       .
       .
       .   
   +-- R1--+
   |       | 
   |  AS1  | 
   |       |
   +-------+

            ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
</t>
<t>
The figure above describes a topology that leads to classic path hunting problem.
In steady state, AS5 has 3 paths for prefixes received from AS1:
</t>
        <texttable>

          <ttcol align="center">Path</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="left">AS_PATH</ttcol>

          <c>p1(best)</c>

          <c>2 1</c>

          <c>p2</c>

          <c>3 2 1</c>

          <c>p3</c>

          <c>4 3 2 1</c>

        </texttable>
<t>

When the link between AS1 and AS2 goes down, it leads to a series of events
and actions at AS5 as follows:
</t>
        <texttable>

          <ttcol align="center">Step</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="left">Event</ttcol>

          <ttcol align="left">Action</ttcol>

          <c>1</c>
          <c>Recv withdraw of p1</c>
          <c>Select p2 as best</c>

          <c> </c>
          <c> </c>
          <c>Send AS_PATH (5 3 2 1) upstream</c>

          <c>--</c>
          <c>--</c>
          <c>--</c>

          <c>2</c>
          <c>Recv withdraw of p2</c>
          <c>Select p3 as best</c>

          <c> </c>
          <c> </c>
          <c>Send AS_PATH (5 4 3 2 1) upstream</c>

          <c>--</c>
          <c>--</c>
          <c>--</c>

          <c>3</c>
          <c>Recv withdraw of p3</c>
          <c>Prefixes have no path</c>

          <c> </c>
          <c> </c>
          <c>Send withdraw for the prefixes upstream</c>

        </texttable>
<t>
This trivial example creates unnecessary churn in the network till the
end state is reached.
</t>
</section>

<section title="SPEAKERID_PATH attribute"
        anchor="SID_PATH">
<t>
SPEAKERID_PATH is an optional transitive attribute that is very similar in encoding
and operation to the AS_PATH attribute. It is composed of a sequence of SPEAKERID path
segments. Each segment is represented by a triple (type, length, value). Following is
the format:
</t>
<t>
      <figure align="center">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[

    0                   1           
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |        Type   |   Length      |
   |   (1 octet)   |  (1 octet)    |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   ~                               ~
   ~             Value             ~
   ~                               ~
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

            ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
</t>
<t>
The type is a 1-octet field with the following value defined:

      <figure align="center">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[

Value         Type definition

  1           AS_ID_SEQUENCE: ordered set of AS and Speaker ID pair
              a route in the UPDATE message has traversed.

            ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
</t>
<t>
The length is a 1-octet field, containing the number of such pairs. Thus when the 
type is 1, the value contains one or more entries of the following:

      <figure align="center">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[

      +---------------------------------+
      |   AS     (4 bytes)              |
      +---------------------------------+
      |   SPEAKER-ID (4 bytes)          |
      +---------------------------------+

            ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
</t>
<t>
The use and meaning of these fields are as follows:
<list style="empty">
<t>AS:
The AS is a four-octet field that indicates the AS
number of the BGP speaker. If this ASN is from the public ASN space,
it must have been assigned by the appropriate authority (use of ASN values
from the private ASN space is strongly discouraged). Note that when a four-octet 
AS supporting speaker (NEW) announces an UPDATE to a two-octet AS
supporting speaker (OLD), it encodes AS_TRANS as a two-octet AS in the
AS_PATH attribute instead of its own AS (<xref target="RFC6793"></xref>).
But while encoding the SPEAKERID_PATH attribute,
it MUST put its own four-octet AS in this field
regardless of whether the neighbor to whom the UPDATE message is being sent is 
an OLD or NEW speaker.
</t>
<t>
SPEAKER-ID:
The SPEAKER-ID is a four-octet field that indicates the router-id
of the BGP speaker. If the router-id is from the public address space, it
must have been assigned by the appropriate authority. (use of the private
ip address as a router-id is strongly discourged).
</t>
</list>
</t>
</section>

<section title="ROOT_CAUSE attribute"
        anchor="ROOT_CAUSE">
<t>
ROOT_CAUSE is an optional transitive attribute that is composed of one or more
triple (type, length, value). Following is the format:
</t>
<t>
      <figure align="center">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[

    0                   1           
    0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   |        Type   |   Length      |
   |   (1 octet)   |  (1 octet)    |
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
   ~                               ~
   ~             Value             ~
   ~                               ~
   +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+

            ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
</t>
<t>
The type is a 1-octet field with the following value defined:

      <figure align="center">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[

Value         Type definition

  1           AS_ID_CONN: AS and router-ID pairs from both sides of the
              connection that is the point of occurrence for the 
              withdraw.

            ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
</t>
<t>
The length is a 1-octet field, containing the length in octets of the value field.
When the type is 1, the value contains the following:

      <figure align="center">
        <artwork align="left"><![CDATA[


      +--------------+
      |Flags(1 octet)|
      +---------------------------------+
      |   left AS     (4 bytes)         |
      +---------------------------------+
      |   left SPEAKER-ID (4 bytes)     |
      +---------------------------------+
      |   right AS    (4 bytes)         |
      +---------------------------------+
      |   right SPEAKER-ID (4 bytes)    |
      +---------------------------------+

            ]]></artwork>
      </figure>
</t>
</section>

<section title="Operation"
        anchor="operation">
<t>
</t>
<section title="Sending SPEAKERID_PATH attribute">
<t>
When a BGP speaker supporting the mechanism described in this document
propagates a route it learned from another BGP speaker's UPDATE message,
it modifies the route's SPEAKERID_PATH attribute by prepending its
own router-ID and AS number as the last pair of the sequence. If there
is no such attribute, the local system creates the attribute, creates a new 
segment in the attribute of type AS_ID_SEQUENCE and places its own pair 
into that segment. If the act of prepending will cause an overflow in
the existing segment (i.e. more than 255 pairs), it MUST prepend a
new segment of type AS_ID_SEQUENCE and prepend its own pair to this new
segment. This operation should be performed regardless of whether the
peer is IBGP or EBGP.
</t>
</section>

<section title="Sending ROOT_CAUSE attribute">
<t>
</t>
<section title="At the point of occurrence">
<t>
A BGP speaker originates the ROOT_CAUSE attribute into an UPDATE message in
one of the following scenarios:
<list style="symbols">
<t> A session with a peer AS goes down or the associated link goes down and 
the received prefixes need to be withdrawn or their bestpath changes.
</t>
<t> it receives withdraws for some prefixes without the ROOT_CAUSE attribute
and they in turn need to be either withdrawn from the ASes upstream or 
re-advertised with new paths.
</t>
</list>
</t>
<t>
While originating the attribute, the speaker encodes the router-ID and AS of
each side of the session.
</t>
</section>

<section title="At an intermediate point">
<t>
Any speaker receiving a withdrawal UPDATE message with ROOT_CAUSE attribute should
preserve and announce the resulting UPDATE message with the same attribute
value. This can be an explicit withdraw for a prefix or an implicit withdraw.
</t>
<t>
Any speaker receiving a reachable UPDATE message with ROOT_CAUSE attribute should
preserve the attribute and not announce the attribute in resulting UPDATE message unless
the resulting UPDATE message is an explicit withdrawal message.
</t>
</section>
</section>

<section title="Receiving ROOT_CAUSE Attribute">
<t>
Whenever a BGP speaker receives an update message to process withdrawn prefixes, it 
does the following:

<list style="symbols">
<t> Remove the BGP path of the prefix withdrawn.
</t>
<t> Find all the other paths that have matching ROOT_CAUSE information
to the one present in path that is removed. Place these paths on an Inactive
timer for an Inactive time interval. Do not select these paths for 
the BGP bespath selection.
</t>
</list>

</t>
</section>

<section title="Usage of BGP Aggregates">
<t>
Whenever a BGP speaker creates an aggregate route from more specific
routes, it will not inherit any BGP SPEAKERID_PATH
information from its more specific routes used for aggregation.

Instead, it will create its own SPEAKERID_PATH attribute when it
announces the aggregate route to its BGP peers, i.e. the attribute
will contain one segment with only its own (AS, router-id) pair when
it announces the aggregate.
</t>
</section>

<section title="BGP Confederation">
<t>
The procedures described above and the new attributes are equally applicable
to confed EBGP and confed IBGP peering sessions.

</t>
</section>

<section title="BGP Inactive Timer">
<t>
BGP inactive timer is used for suppressing path information from being used 
in BGP bestpath selection. This prevents BGP from selecting such alternate 
paths for which withdrawals are not received yet. A BGP speaker should 
remove suppress paths whenever withdrawn. A BGP speaker must subject all
the suppress paths for BGP bestpath selection if they are not withdrawn 
even after inactive timer expires. 

The timeout for an Inactive Timer should be kept big enough to allow the
withdrawal information to propagate across the AS.
</t>
</section>

</section>

<section anchor="deployment_consideration"
            title="Deployment Considerations">
<t>
</t>
</section>

  <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
   <t>The authors would like to thank Robert Raszuk and Pedro Marques
    for their input.</t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
   <t>IANA  shall   assign  codepoints  for   the  SPEAKERID_PATH  and
    ROOT_CAUSE attributes.   These codepoints will come  from the "BGP
    Path Attributes" registry.</t>
  </section>

  <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
   <t>This extension  to BGP does  not change the  underlying security
    issues.</t>
  </section>
 </middle>

  <!--  *****BACK MATTER ***** -->

  <back>
    <!-- References split into informative and normative -->

    <!-- There are 2 ways to insert reference entries from the citation libraries:
    1. define an ENTITY at the top, and use "ampersand character"RFC2629;
        here (as shown)
    2. simply use a PI
        "less than character"?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119.xml"?> here
        (for I-Ds:
          include="reference.I-D.narten-iana-considerations-rfc2434bis.xml")

    Both are cited textually in the same manner: by using xref elements.
    If you use the PI option, xml2rfc will, by default, try to find included
    files in the same directory as the including file. You can also define
    the XML_LIBRARY environment variable
    with a value containing a set of directories to search.  These can be
    either in the local
    filing system or remote ones accessed by http (http://domain/dir/... ).-->

  <references title="Normative References">
   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2439"?>
   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4271"?>
   <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6793"?>
  </references>

  <references title="Informative References">
   <?rfc include="reference.I-D.li-bgp-stability"?>
  </references>
    <!-- Change Log

v00 2008-10-01  KP    Initial version
v01 2008-10-25  PM    Revised version
    -->
  </back>
</rfc>
